<?xml-model href="RelaxNGExercise2.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
   
<source>
  
    <titlelevel"poem">Leaves</titlelevel> 
    <author>Lloyd Schwartz</author>
    -<date when="1941"/> 
</source>
    <para1> 1 Every
          
    <month>October</month> it becomes important, no, necessary to see the leaves turning, to be
        surrounded by leaves turning; it's not just the symbolism, to confront in the
            <neg>death</neg> of the year your<neg> death</neg>, one blazing farewell appearance,
        though the irony isn't lost on you that nature is most seductive when it's about to
            <neg>die</neg>, flaunting the dazzle of its incipient exit, an ending that at least so
        far the effects of human progress <neg>(pollution, acid rain)</neg> have not yet frightened
        you enough to make you believe is real; that is, you know this ending is a
            <neg>deception</neg> because of course nature is always renewing itself— the trees
            don't<neg> die</neg>, they just pretend, go out in style, and return in style: a new
        style</para1>. <para2>2 Is it deliberate how far they make you go especially if you live in
        the <place>city</place> to get far enough away from <place>home</place> to see not just
        trees but only trees? The boring <trail>highways</trail>, roadsigns, high speeds, 10-axle
            <transport>trucks</transport> passing you as if they were in an even greater hurry than
        you to look at leaves: so you <action>drive</action> in <neg>terror</neg> for literal
            <time>hours</time> and it looks like <weather>rain</weather>, or
        <element>snow</element>, but it's probably just clouds (too cloudy to see any color?) and
        you wonder, given the <neg>poverty</neg> of your memory, which <trail>road</trail> had the
        most color last year, but it doesn't matter since you're probably too late anyway, or too
        early— whichever <trail>road</trail> you take will be the wrong one and you've probably come
        all this way for nothing. </para2>
    <para3> 3 You'll be <action>driving</action> along <neg>depressed</neg> when suddenly a cloud
        will move and the sun will muscle through and ignite the<trail> hills</trail>. It may not
        last. Probably won't last. But for a moment the whole <place>world</place> comes to. Wakes
        up. Proves it lives. It lives— <color>red, yellow, orange, brown, russet, ocher, vermilion,
            gold</color>. Flame and rust. Flame and rust, the permutations of burning.
            <self>You're</self> on fire. <self>Your</self> eyes are on fire. It won't last,
            <self>you</self> don't want it to last. <self>You</self> can't stand any more. But
            <self>you</self> don't want it to stop. It's what <self>you've</self> come for. It's
        what <self>you'll</self> come back for. It won't stay with <self>you</self>, but
            <self>you'll </self> remember that it felt like nothing else<self> you've</self> felt or
        something <self>you've</self> felt that also didn't last.</para3> Copyright © 1992
    <!-- 92' was a great year --> by Lloyd Schwartz. From Goodnight, Gracie (The University of
    Chicago Press, 1992). Appears courtesy of the author. </source>
    </xml>

